A Guide to the Records of the Policy Office: Clemency and Extradition Files of Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder, 1990-1994
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Policy Office: Clemency and Extradition Files of Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder, 1990-1994
The Library of Virginia
35539
20.65 cu. ft. (63 boxes)
Virginia. Governor (1990-1994: Wilder)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The records must be reviewed by staff for personal and medical privacy protected information before serving.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder on 31 October 1996.
Biographical Information
Lawrence Douglas Wilder was born in Richmond, Va., on January 17, 1931. He graduated from Virginia Union University in 1951 and afterwards was drafted into the Army, where he served in the Korean War from 1952-1953 and received a bronze star. He then attended the Howard University School of Law and graduated in 1959. Douglas Wilder was elected to the Virginia Senate in 1969 as the first African American member since Reconstruction and served in the Senate for five terms. In 1985, he was elected to the office of Lieutenant Governor as the first African American to be elected to statewide office in Virginia. L. Douglas Wilder won the election for Governor of Virginia in 1989 and served from January 13, 1990 to January 14, 1994. He was the first African American to be elected as Governor in United States.
During the Wilder Administration, the Policy Office was headed by Walter McFarlane, Executive Assistant for Policy, and four Special Assistants: Richard Taylor (Health and Human Resources, and Education), Robert Blue (Finance and Natural Resources), Jeff Nuechterlein (Economic Development and Transportation), and Lynne Porfiri (Administration and Public Safety). The Policy Office was responsible for review and coordination of all policy matters, including: review of proposed legislation from agencies and Cabinet; formulation of the Governor's legislative initiatives; tracking legislation and serving as legislative liaison; review of General Assembly approved legislation submitted to the Governor for signature, amendment or veto; review of death penalty clemency requests, as well as other pardon and restoration of rights requests; review of legal settlements and other legal matters from the Office of the Attorney General's Office; review of proposed regulations; review of all matters pertaining to the judiciary and writs of habeas corpus; review of proposed executive orders; assistance with speech writing; serving as staff for Governor's special commissions; administrative support for Governor's Fellows program; serving as special interest liaison; acting as in-house counsel; and all correspondence with policy implications or pertaining to sensitive or controversial issues requiring legal overview.
Scope and Content
Records of the Policy Office: Clemency and Extradition Files, 1990-1994, of Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder. The collection is housed in 63 boxes and arranged into three series. Series have been designated for: Series I: Extraditions and Writs of Habeas Corpus; Series II: Clemency Files; and Series III: Restoration of Rights. The records must be reviewed by staff for personal and medical privacy protected information before serving.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Extraditions and Writs of Habeas Corpus
Series II: Clemency Petitions
Series III: Restoration of Rights
Contents List
- Series I: Extraditions and Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1990-1993., Extent: 1.3 cu. ft. (4 boxes) (Box Boxes 1-4)
  Records of the Policy Office: Extraditions and Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1990-1993, of Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder. The records are organized alphabetically into 4 boxes. The Extraditions mostly contain memorandum from Walter McFarlane, Executive Assistant for Policy, detailing the name of the prisoner, the state which was requesting extradition, and stating the recommendation of the Attorney General. A few of the files include a copy of the extradition request and a prisoner profile. The Writs of Habeas Corpus include correspondence, prisoner profiles, memorandum, and a copy of the writ.
  The records must be reviewed by staff for personal and medical privacy protected information before serving.
  - Extraditions, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Extraditions, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Extraditions, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Extraditions, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Extraditions, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1990 January-June (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1990 July-September (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1990 October-December (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1991 January-March (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1991 April-June (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1991 July-August (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1991 September-December (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1992 January-February (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1992 March-May (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1992 June-September (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1992 October-December (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1993 January-February (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1993 March (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1993 April-May (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1993 June-July (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1993 August-December (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Writs of Habeas Corpus, Incomplete, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Series II: Clemency Petitions, 1990-1994., Extent: 19.6 cu. ft. (56 boxes). (Box 5-60)
  The records must be reviewed for privacy information before being served. Files may contain psychological and physical examination reports, prisoner records, social security numbers, crime scene photographs, and attorney-client privileged information.
  This series contains clemency petitions from prisoners submitted to the Governor. The clemency petitions usually include: petition from prisoner, constituent letters (for and against clemency), court documents and opinions, summary of the case provided by the Office of the Attorney General, and a memorandum to the Governor providing background information on the case, anaylsis of petition and conclusion/recommendation to Governor.
  Clemency petitions and/or correspondence for Capital Punishment cases were submitted on behalf of: Bassette, Herbert R. (clemency granted 1992); Boggs, Richard T. (executed 1990 July 19); Bunch, Timothy Dale (executed 1992 December 10); Chabrol, Andrew John (executed 1993 June 17); Clozza, Albert J. (executed 1991 July 24); Coleman, Roger Keith (executed 1992 May 20); Correll, Walter Milton, Jr. (executed 1996 January 4); Davidson, Mickey Wayne (executed 1995 October 19); Delong, Wayne Kenneth (suicide); Evans, Wilbert Lee (executed 1990 October 17); Fitzgerald, Edward B. (executed 1992 July 23); George, Michael Carl (executed 1997 February 6); Giarratano, Joseph (commuted February 1991); Jones, Willie Leroy (executed 1992 September 11); Justus, Buddy Earl (executed 1990 December 13); Peterson, Derick Lynn (executed 1991 August 22); Poyner, Syvasky L. (executed 1993 March 18); Pruett, David Mark (executed 1993 December 16); Savino, Joseph John, III (executed 1996 July 17); Snyder, Walter Tyrone (pardoned 1993 April 23); Spencer, Timothy Wilson (executed 1994 April 27); Stamper, Charles S. (executed 1993 January 19); Velasquez, Alex M. (conditional clemency 1992 November 25, died 1993 April 14); and Wise, Joe Lewis (executed 1993 September 14).
  Arranged alphabetically by prisoners last name into two subseries: Subseries A: Capital Punishment Files and Subseries B: General Files.
  - Subseries A: Capital Punishment Files
    - Bassette, Herbert R., 1992 (Box 5)
    - Boggs, Richard Thomas, 1990 (Box 6-7)
    - Bunch, Timothy Dale, 1992 (Box 8-11)
    - Chabrol, Andrew John, 1993 (Box 12)
    - Clozza, Albert J., 1991 (Box 13)
    - Coleman, Roger Keith, 1992 (Box 14-19)
    - Correll, Walter Milton, Jr., 1990 (Box 20)
    - Davidson, Mickey Wayne, 1993 (Box 21)
    - Delong, Wayne Kenneth (Box 22)
    - Evans, Wilbert Lee, 1990 (Box 23-26)
    - Fitzgerald, Edward B., 1992 (Box 27-29)
    - George, Michael Carl, 1993 (Box 30)
    - Giarratano, Joseph, 1991 (Box 30a)
    - Jones, Willie Leroy, 1992 (Box 31-33)
    - Justus, Buddy Earl, 1990 (Box 34)
    - Peterson, Derick Lynn, 1991 (Box 35-37)
    - Poyner, Syvasky L., 1993 (Box 38-40)
    - Pruett, David Mark, 1993 (Box 41-42)
    - Savino, Joseph John, III, 1990 (Box 43)
    - Snyder, Walter Tyrone, 1993 (Box 44)
    - Spencer, Timothy Wilson, 1993 (Box 45)
    - Stamper, Charles S., 1992 (Box 46-51)
    - Velasquez, Alex, 1992 (Box 52)
    - Wise, Joe Lewis, 1993 (Box 53-54)
  - Subseries B: General Files
    - Adolf, Jerry, 1993 (Box 55, Folder 1)
    - Allen, Howard, 1992 (Box 55, Folder 2)
    - Anderson, Carnell, 1993 (Box 55, Folder 3)
    - Anderson, Marvin Lamont, 1993 (Box 55, Folder 4-8)
    - Anthony, Mark, 1993 (Box 56, Folder 1)
    - Austin, Robert, 1993 (Box 56, Folder 2)
    - Billington, Michael, 1993 (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - Brady, Kenneth E., Jr., 1992 (Box 56, Folder 4)
    - Brown, Fred Jackson, 1993 (Box 56, Folder 5)
    - Brown, Patrick J., 1993 (Box 56, Folder 6)
    - Bullock, Samuel, 1993 (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - Chrisman, Charles D., 1993 (Box 56, Folder 8)
    - Clark, John Edward, Jr., 1993 (Box 56, Folder 9)
    - Crawford, Leland D., 1992 (Box 56, Folder 10)
    - Creekmur, William Rogers, 1993 (Box 56, Folder 11)
    - Crowe, Raymond P., Jr., 1993 (Box 56, Folder 12)
    - Currie, Reznick, 1993 (Box 56, Folder 13)
    - Curtis, Kevin D., 1993 (Box 56, Folder 14)
    - Davis, Michael, 1993 (Box 56, Folder 15)
    - Davis, Wallace S., 1992 (Box 56, Folder 16)
    - DeLaoch, Glen, 1993 (Box 56, Folder 17)
    - Delk, Stevie, 1993 (Box 56, Folder 18)
    - Dillard, Patricia, 1993 (Box 56, Folder 19)
    - Dunn, Thomas, 1993 (Box 56, Folder 20)
    - Epps, Charles H., 1993 (Box 56, Folder 21)
    - Ferguson, Robert L., 1992 (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - Fettig, Kerry A., 1992 (Box 57, Folder 2)
    - Fitz, Michael S., 1993 (Box 57, Folder 3)
    - Fletcher, Gergory, 1993 (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - Foreman, Patrick, 1993 (Box 57, Folder 5)
    - Forsythe, Joseph, 1993 (Box 57, Folder 6)
    - Fuller, Robert, 1993 (Box 57, Folder 7)
    - Gay, James F., 1993 (Box 57, Folder 8)
    - Geesy, Harry, 1993 (Box 57, Folder 9)
    - Gentry, John, 1993 (Box 57, Folder 10)
    - Gilliam, Olivia Little, 1993 (Box 57, Folder 11)
    - Graham, Kenneth E., 1994 (Box 57, Folder 12)
    - Hart, Herbert H., 1993 (Box 57, Folder 13)
    - Hatcher, Bruce A., 1993 (Box 57, Folder 14)
    - Hatcher, Kenneth E., 1993 (Box 57, Folder 15)
    - Hill, Michael L., 1993 (Box 57, Folder 16)
    - Holliday, Charles, 1993 (Box 57, Folder 17)
    - Hudnall, Vermidell, 1993 (Box 57, Folder 18)
    - Islam, Mohammed A., 1993 (Box 57, Folder 19)
    - Iverson, Allen, 1993 (Box 57, Folder 20)
    - Jackson, Sandra, 1993 (Box 57, Folder 21)
    - Jefferson, Charles W., IV, 1993 (Box 57, Folder 22)
    - Johnson, Cylde, Sr., 1992 (Box 57, Folder 23)
    - Johnson, Edward T., 1992 (Box 58, Folder 1)
    - Johnson, Richard, Jr., 1991 (Box 58, Folder 2)
    - Johnson, Sandra, 1992 (Box 58, Folder 3)
    - Jones, Donald, 1992 (Box 58, Folder 4)
    - Jones, Morris, 1992 (Box 58, Folder 5)
    - Kelliher, Charles, 1991 (Box 58, Folder 6)
    - Kelly, Calvin J., 1990 (Box 58, Folder 7)
    - Kennon, Suzanne, 1993 (Box 58, Folder 8)
    - Koury, Roger, Sr., 1992 (Box 58, Folder 9)
    - Life, Vicky, 1993 (Box 58, Folder 10)
    - Lovitt, Anthony D., 1992 (Box 58, Folder 11)
    - Maryland, Andrew M., 1992 (Box 58, Folder 12)
    - Mackenzie, Seth Dabney, 1993 (Box 58, Folder 13-14)
    - Maker, Robert, 1993 (Box 58, Folder 15)
    - Martin, Joseph N., 1993 (Box 59, Folder 1-2)
    - Martin, Ralph, 1993 (Box 59, Folder 3)
    - Miller, Lisa, 1993 (Box 59, Folder 4)
    - Miller, Mark A., 1993 (Box 59, Folder 5)
    - Miltier, Joseph E., 1991 (Box 59, Folder 6)
    - Minor, Walter, Jr., 1992 (Box 59, Folder 7)
    - Mitchell, Arthur E., 1993 (Box 59, Folder 8)
    - Moore, Vernon, 1993 (Box 59, Folder 9)
    - Morton, John, 1993 (Box 59, Folder 10)
    - Mullins, Cynthia Lynn Tucker, 1992 (Box 59, Folder 11)
    - Murray, Ross Richard, 1991 (Box 59, Folder 12)
    - Myers, Kevin Brian, 1993 (Box 59, Folder 13)
    - Neal, Charles, 1993 (Box 59, Folder 14)
    - Nelson, Ricky, 1993 (Box 59, Folder 15)
    - Nelson, Roger Lee, 1993 (Box 59, Folder 16)
    - Newton, Edward C., IV, 1991 (Box 59, Folder 17)
    - Norwood, Bobby, 1993 (Box 59, Folder 18)
    - Paley, Michael Linwood, 1993 (Box 59, Folder 19)
    - Parker, Richard, 1993 (Box 59, Folder 20)
    - Pettus, Thomas R., 1993 (Box 59, Folder 21)
    - Pinto, Moshe, 1991 (Box 59, Folder 22)
    - Pomerantz, Arthur, 1993 (Box 59, Folder 23)
    - Powell, Roger, 1993 (Box 59, Folder 24)
    - Puryear, Garland, 1993 (Box 59, Folder 25)
    - Reznick, Currie, 1993 (Box 60, Folder 1)
    - Robinson, James, 1993 (Box 60, Folder 2)
    - Satchell, Charles, 1993 (Box 60, Folder 3)
    - Saunders, Walter Jerome, Jr., 1992 (Box 60, Folder 4)
    - Scaggs, Timothy L., 1993 (Box 60, Folder 5)
    - Scales, Shawn, 1993 (Box 60, Folder 6)
    - Sharp, Mike, 1991 (Box 60, Folder 7)
    - Simmons, Michael, and Wynn, Samuel, 1993-1994 (Box 60, Folder 8)
    - Sindram, Michael, 1992 (Box 60, Folder 9)
    - Smith, James Arnold David, 1993 (Box 60, Folder 10)
    - Speck, Dennis E., 1992 (Box 60, Folder 11)
    - St. Clair, Howard Allen, 1993 (Box 60, Folder 12)
    - Stephens, Robert, 1993 (Box 60, Folder 13)
    - Taylor, Alphonzo, Sr., 1993 (Box 60, Folder 14)
    - Taylor, Marie Lee, 1993 (Box 60, Folder 15)
    - Teel, Lisa Dallas, 1993 (Box 60, Folder 16)
    - Terry, William C., 1993 (Box 60, Folder 17)
    - Turner, John W. 1991 (Box 60, Folder 18)
    - Vaughn, Gilbert L., 1993 (Box 60, Folder 19)
    - Warren, Dorothea, 1992 (Box 60, Folder 20)
    - Washington, Melvin D., 1993 (Box 60, Folder 21)
    - Williamson, Willie J., 1990 (Box 60, Folder 22-23)
    - Wills, Michael P., 1993 (Box 60, Folder 24)
    - Wright, Gregory S., 1993 (Box 60, Folder 25)
    - Wyatt, Dewayne Alan, 1993 (Box 60, Folder 26)
- Series III: Restoration of Rights, 1990-1993., Extent: 1.05 cu. ft. (3 boxes). (Box 61-63)
  This series contains records relating to pardons and restorations of rights submitted to the Governor. Also included are correspondence and memorandum regarding clemency and other policies from the Secretary of the Commonwealth.
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Administrative Law Appendix, Review, 1992 (Box 61, Folder 1)
  - Conflict of Interest statements, 1990 (Box 61, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 61, Folder 3)
  - Escaped inmates, Kelleher, Charles, 1990 (Box 61, Folder 4)
  - Escaped inmates, Daniels, Ruben, 1990 (Box 61, Folder 5)
  - Escaped inmates, Smith, Oliver, 1990 (Box 61, Folder 6)
  - Escaped inmates, Williamson, Willie, 1990 (Box 61, Folder 7)
  - Executive Clemency, 1990 (Box 61, Folder 8)
  - Executive Clemency, 1991 (Box 61, Folder 9)
  - Executive Clemency, 1992 (Box 61, Folder 10)
  - Extraditions, 1990 (Box 61, Folder 11)
  - Finalization of Appointment of Escheators, 1990 (Box 61, Folder 12)
  - Firearms policy, 1988-1991 (Box 61, Folder 13)
  - Form letters, 1990 (Box 61, Folder 14)
  - General, 1990 (Box 61, Folder 15)
  - Inmate mail, 1990 (Box 62, Folder 1)
  - List of Removal of Political Disabilities from 1970 to 1990 (Box 62, Folder 2)
  - Memorandum, 1992 (Box 62, Folder 3-4)
  - Pardons and Restoration of Rights, 1990 (Box 62, Folder 5-6)
  - Pardons and Restoration of Rights, 1990-1991 (Box 62, Folder 7-8)
  - Requisition, 1991 (Box 63, Folder 1)
  - Restoration of Rights, 1990-1992 (Box 63, Folder 2)
  - Restoration of Rights, 1992 (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - Restoration of Rights, 1993 (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - Travel order requests policy, 1990 (Box 63, Folder 5)